"How to Get the Ideal Ferritin Level
and Avoid Symptoms of Iron Deficiency"
As I discussed
in my last video,
iron can be
a double-edged sword.
It's an essential mineral,
but simultaneously a danger
as a pro-oxidant;
so, our body tries
to regulate levels
but can really only do that
through altering
how much iron we absorb.
We don't have a mechanism
to get rid of excess iron;
so, it accumulates
because, like calories,
it was better evolutionarily
to have too much
rather than too little.
So, as we age, our iron stores
get higher and higher.
For men, it starts
immediately in adulthood,
and women begin to catch up
after they stop menstruating.
Remember, in my last video,
I explored
the evidence suggesting
that the ideal ferritin level—
the sweet spot—
is between 15 and 50,
but the average level
may be higher than that.
Why would we evolve
to accumulate
potentially toxic levels?
Most of the iron in our bodies
is in our blood,
and we can lose it
in significant amounts
rather abruptly.
And our ability
to make new blood from iron
is 20 times faster
than we can absorb it.
Therefore, our ability
to store some excess iron
became
an evolutionary advantage,
allowing for rapid recovery
from an unexpected loss
of blood.
Unfortunately,
that comes at a cost.
Carrying excess iron
puts us at elevated risk
because of all the free radicals
it generates.
So, what was once
a valuable survival mechanism
has become an anachronism.
Today, we can replace lost blood
with a transfusion;
so, we no longer have to keep
these high stores of iron.
So, we're left with the risks
without the benefits.
Now, if you're above that
15 to 50 ferritin sweet spot,
donating blood
is always an option—
a safe, feasible,
and inexpensive way
to rid yourself of excess iron,
and it's a mitzvah!
Or, you can reduce
your meat consumption
and lower iron levels that way
to gain health benefits,
especially if you aren't losing
blood naturally every month.
Our body is better able
to regulate the absorption
of the proper amount
of the non-heme iron
concentrated in plant foods
rather than the heme iron
found predominantly
in blood and muscle.
But you can go too low.
The World Health Organization
defines low ferritin
as levels under 15,
and vegetarians are more likely
to fall below that,
especially menstruating women.
But does having low iron stores
cause problems
if you don't become anemic—
meaning as long
as your blood counts are okay?
If you run
a social media poll,
iron-deficient women self-report
a wide range of symptoms,
but some are so nonspecific,
like fatigue,
it's hard to know
if low iron's the cause.
What we need
is a study like this,
comparing the health
and well-being
of hundreds of women
who fall under
the ferritin level of 15,
with depleted iron stores,
versus those with larger,
sufficient iron stores.
The only significant difference
between iron-depleted
and iron-sufficient women
concerned memory disorders,
which were
significantly less common
in iron-depleted women.
So, the iron-deficient women
appeared to have
better memory.
Here's what
the researchers found.
No significant difference
between low
and normal iron stores
when it came
to having palpitations,
their general feeling
about their health status,
their inability
to concentrate,
and sleeping disorders,
but there was
apparently better memory
among the iron depleted,
yet no significant difference
for vertigo, fainting,
nervousness,
thinned spoon-like fingernails,
or inflammation
of the lips or tongue.
And no significant difference
was seen in physical health,
mental health, social health,
general health,
perceived health, self-esteem,
anxiety, depression,
pain, or disability.
And finally,
no significant difference
in the rates of infections,
including
respiratory infections,
bladder infections,
other infections,
having to see a doctor
or other health professionals,
being in the hospital,
having to take sick leave,
or having a fever.
In other words, there appears
to be no conclusive evidence
that an absence of iron stores
has negative consequences.
But that's just
our backup iron stores,
our ferritin level.
If our iron gets too low,
we can actually become anemic,
where we don't have enough iron
to make blood,
and that can have
serious consequences.
Are vegetarians more likely
to become anemic?
And, regardless,
what's the best way to treat it?
I'll answer
those questions, next.